Guide to the NYU Abu Dhabi Capstone Archives AD.MC.004
NYU Abu Dhabi, Archives and Special Collections
- Arts & Humanities Division Projects, 2014-2021
  - Literature and Creative Writing
    - Joaquin, Nikki. Hawak, 2020; 2020-0030 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2020-0030)
      "Hawak" is a novella about an aswang, a local monster from Filipino urban legend that feeds on unborn children, that awakens in modern-day Baguio city. It is a story about female communities and bridging gaps between women of different social backgrounds through the body of the monster. It seeks to retake ownership over the figure of the aswang that has long been transformed after years of colonization in order to address modern issues that women face today. "Hawak" also serves as a response to Filipino Literary History that hopes to expand the role of women and their characterization, transitioning from the domestic and expanding outwards into the world.
      Aswang, Filipino, Mythology, Feminism, Language, Community, Philippines, Novella, Transformation, Monster
    - John, Neha. The Sample Book, 2020; 2020-0029 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2020-0029)
      The Sample Book' is a manuscript of prose, lists and collections of my memories of growing up in Dubai. It is an attempt at recording the ordinary in order not to forget or be forgotten.
      Identity/Dubai/Memory/Belonging/Place/UAE/Expat/Migration
    - Lambert, Lucius. What Remains: الطلل, 2020; 2020-0034 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2020-0034)
      This capstone examines how Hurricane Katrina (and natural disasters in general) impacted cultural transmission in the Lebanese diaspora in Mississippi.
      Diaspora, Lebanese, Immigrant, Katrina, Natural Disaster, Cultural Transmission
    - Patterson, Zoe. Na'ila's Eyes, 2020; 2020-0033 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2020-0033)
      If you have ever lived in Al Ain then you know it's not really a place. Al Ain is an event in your life and once it's over you look back on it with the same incredulous wonder that you might consider a vivid dream. My capstone is a novel that explores Al Ain and the unseen djinn city that exists on the other side of it: Na'ila. Harper is a young woman from Canada who escapes her small-town life by agreeing to study for a semester at a university in Al Ain. Aisha is a young djinn who has just received her visa to enter Na'ila where she'll be working as a maid for one of the most powerful djinn families: the Raaeds. Their stories intertwine when Aisha begins to visit Al Ain and Harper falls in love with Majed-- one of the Raaed brothers. When Harper finds out she's pregnant the Raaeds decide the baby belongs to them. Aisha might be the only one who can keep Harper and the baby safe.
    - Raj Pandey, Chiran. "In accord with more universal vibrations": Totality, Race, and Gender in Teju Cole's Open City, 2020; 2020-0026 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2020-0026)
      My capstone offers a reading of the 2011 novel Open City by Teju Cole through the lens of aesthetic theory and the concept of novelistic totality. The problem animating my paper is the rape of Moji Kasali, a Nigerian acquaintance of the novel's narrator, Julius. Moji accuses Julius of having raped her when he was fourteen and she fifteen. My capstone is shaped by Moji's accusation. In my paper, I consider Moji's rape to be the founding rupture of the novel: Open City arises, in other words, in response to this disastrous event in Moji's and Julius's lives. Troubled by the rape — which he has forgotten — and by its reminder through Moji's accusation, Julius, I suggest, writes Open City as an attempt to recreate the innocent, pre-lapsarian wholeness that was lost when he raped Moji. Along the way his attempt at totality is disturbed by race, gender, history, all three embodied foremost by Moji.
      race, gender, totality, aesthetic theory, sublime, history
    - Satterfield, Scout. The End of the World and Other Experiments, 2020; 2020-0032 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2020-0032)
      This collection of short stories explores form, style and voice in storytelling.
      Short story, Creative writing
    - Sinha, Vamika. Cranes, 2020; 2020-0023 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2020-0023)
      Cranes is a collection of poetry and creative non-fiction bridging cosmopolitanism and women of color (WOC). Spanning four sections – taking off, flight, orbit, and land – the book follows the voice of a flâneuse, navigating different "cosmopolitan" cities like Abu Dhabi, New York, and Paris. But all cities have histories, which have created different unjust systems that affect the WOC's mobility and conception of self today. How can her body then exist with difference, and still keep and construct her own autonomous identity, intact? I argue for love, the creative space, and community as solutions, spaces where the WOC can rebuild a self on her own terms.
      cosmopolitanism, race, gende,r feminism, poetry, manuscript, women of color, flânerie, identity
    - Abdel-Ghaffar, Malak. Amani, 2021; 2021-0042 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2021-0042)
      Amani is a young adult novella about three girls who share the same soul. Amani is a middle-class 17-year-old who stumbles upon a BuzzFeed quiz that asks whether she's curious about her fate. Curious, Amani starts a free trial that embarks her on a journey of seeing and constructing her alternate lives: Naima and Amina. As the trial counts down, Amani decides and observes a snapshot of an event that happens every year in each of the girls' lives. The trial is counting down, and Amani has to decide her favorite fate. Which will she decide? And what will it be based on? This novella digs deep into how privilege and choice come in various shapes and forms and highlights the reality of how humans react to the environments they find themselves in.
      Author provided keywords: Amani, BuzzFeed, Naima, Amina, Egypt, Class, Destiny, Free Trial
    - Abi Samra, Tom. Between and Across the ʿAjāʾib, Riḥla, and Kommentaranthologie Traditions: Toward an Encyclopedic Reading of Yūsuf al-Shirbīnī's Hazz al-quḥūf (fl. 1686), 2021; 2021-0043 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2021-0043)
      In this thesis I propose to read Yūsuf al-Shirbīnī's Hazz al-quḥūf (fl. 1686) in light of the encyclopedic ethos that permeated the postclassical period (13th–18th centuries) in Arabic literary history. In the introduction, I show that scholars have considered it either a historical text or a literary one—but never both (or neither). I situate Hazz in the ʿajāʾib and riḥla traditions to explore questions of fact, fiction, ethnography, and, ultimately, encyclopedism. I read al-Shirbīnī contra Evliya Çelebi's Seyahâtnâme. This reading reveals a textual epistemology that is not concerned with fact per se, but with truth-value. Next, I turn to the questions of structure and genre; I explore the structure of Hazz. I draw on Gilles Deleuze and Félix Guattari's notion of the rhizome to theorize the structure of the Kommentaranthologie. I also engage Jacques Derrida's discussion of the "supplement" and his "law of genre" to theorize how Hazz exceeds the genre it situates itself in. I then speculate about the possible social purpose of the text's structure. Finally, I reflect on this thesis's contribution to undoing the problematic inḥiṭāṭ narrative, and explore alternative pathways to problematize this paradigm by situating the text within (a) Mediterranean literary history.
      Author provided keywords: literary commentaries, Ottoman Arabic literature, postclassical Arabic literature, genre, encyclopedism
    - Alhamali, Einas. An English Translation of Christmas in Mecca by Ahmad Khairi Al-Omari, 2021; 2021-0041 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2021-0041)
      My Capstone is a translation of some parts of the Arabic novel Christmas fi Mecca, or Christmas in Mecca. A diasporic Iraqi family, torn by war, reunites in Mecca over Christmas break. Western and Arab traditions, habits, and values collide in the individual family members, and the regrets of the past linger along with the uncertainties of the present. This novel explores family ties, the history of Baghdad, and the relationships between different religious sects, as told by five character perspectives.
      Author provided keywords: translation, diaspora, tone, footnotes, iraq, christmas, mecca
    - Almosa, Nada. Television Dreams & Other Poems, 2021; 2021-0037 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2021-0037)
      A collection of poetry using cross-genre writing, documentary poetry, and verbatim writing to explore rage and haunting in the context of diasporic queer Palestinian experience.
      Author provided keywords: Diaspora, Queer, Media, Verbatim, Poetry, Documentary
    - Bhatra, Bhrigu. Painful Laughter: An Analysis of Comedy in the Discourse of #MeToo, 2021; 2021-0040 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2021-0040)
      This capstone project is a comparative analysis of two recent and extremely popular standup comedy specials, The Bird Revelation by Dave Chappelle and Nanette by Hannah Gadsby. My analysis uncovers how these comedians engage with the #MeToo movement using standup comedy and highlights the comic strategies they use to make their argument onstage and off. A hallmark of these specials is the willingness of the comedian to make the audience feel uncomfortable, which results in quite unique comedy specials that make several formal innovations. Ultimately, what the comedians argue in their specials has consequences for how we consider standup comedy and its potential for social reform in the #MeToo era.
      Author provided keywords: Comedy, #MeToo, Dave Chappelle, Hannah Gadsby, Rhetoric, Pain
    - Lim, Chaerin. Afterwards: Five Tales Written in the After, 2021; 2021-0036 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2021-0036)
      This short story collection is a personal project that reflects on and records specific moments that I have experienced during my time at NYUAD, but in fictionalized form. It is a diary that records striking or overwhelming memories that have pushed me to reevaluate what to hold on in life. By writing these tales, I aimed to move away from the memories that each character manifests, and towards an afterwards; the fact that there exists such an afterwards—that I got to step away from the past and materialize snippets of valuable thoughts and feelings on paper—is what matters. The project consists of a lyric poem and five short stories that are different in setting, narrative style and form, and point of view. While each story centers on the keyword of "after-life," it also stretches for something bigger than the boundaries of an afterlife. Each character encounters some experience with death, but more so, find themselves alone and isolated from the rest of the world. Join these vulnerable characters on a journey of loneliness and fragility, as they navigate and grapple their way through life and contemplate what is to be left afterwards.
      Author provided keywords: afterlife, loneliness, vulnerability, loss
    - Menon, Andy V. Poothan and Thira, 2021; 2021-0039 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2021-0039)
      This submission from my novella is inspired by the mythology of the small village of Thozupadam in the state of Kerala, India. At the centre of the lore and legends lies the Poothan and Thira, an artistic ritual performance that has been around for over 200 years. This novella aims to reflect the village's growing concerns about religious and cultural heritage disappearing, by following the life of a boy named Kutty and his family who have inherited the ritual. When prompted by a choice between preserving tradition and promising opportunities outside the village, Kutty's beliefs in the village gods, demons, and magic stagger as he grows. The ghouls of the village send one of their own, Poothan, on a task to regain Kutty's faith. The supernatural entities must ensure that the boy fulfils his fate of inheriting the ritual himself so that the cycle of tradition is undisrupted, and so that their survival is not threatened, even if revival requires unorthodox means.
      Author provided keywords: Folklore, Kerala, Heritage, Fiction, Ritual, Tradition
    - Nirmala Dious, Aathma. Thoo!, 2021; 2021-0038 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2021-0038)
      In an alternate timeline, the city of Abu Dhabi is made out of buildings controlled by the PES, a mechanical system that expels residents from their apartments when it is their time to leave. The fictional novel follows Anaswara, a Malayali expat woman born and brought up in this city. Anaswara is now a 25-year old researcher who digs deeper into her childhood home and writes about her life in the PES. However, her past comes crashing into the present when an old friend, Nourah, contacts her to help with an investigation that connects together a series of deaths from 2008, to the PES system crash in 2015—the same one that forced Anaswara and her family out of Abu Dhabi. This capstone is a novel-in-progress and what you read is about 1/3rd of the complete novel.
      Author provided keywords: Creative Writing, novel, speculative fiction, Abu Dhabi, Gulf Literature
    - Talavera, Leanne. Writings of Oceania: Examining Postcolonial Identity in Satendra Nandan's "The Wounded Sea", 2021; 2021-0045 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2021-0045)
      Oceanian studies, particularly under Epeli Hau'ofa, has traditionally looked at identity through the ocean and land— land as the root of Oceanian history and culture, ocean as an extension of those roots. Additionally, the field has been characterized by its rejection of misconceived Oceanian "smallness," which has belittled the region socio-politically and geographically. But if scholars such as Epeli Hau'ofa refer to Oceanian lands as the root of Oceanian identity, then what of those who, under colonialism, were forcibly brought to labor on that very land? This paper seeks to expand upon such frameworks of Oceanian postcolonial studies in regard to identity and "smallness," and aims to examine them through an analysis of Satendra Nandan's "The Wounded Sea". Firstly, this paper argues that "The Wounded Sea" explores Oceanian identity on the national and regional level; and, that the novel not only interrogates the pillars of Oceanian identity— land and ocean— but also renders them active agents in reasserting Indo-Fijian belonging. Secondly, this paper argues that the "The Wounded Sea" is an Oceanian novel that pushes back against conceived Oceanian "smallness," by engaging in wider discourses of literature and genre, and ultimately situating itself in a larger postcolonial literary tradition.
      Author provided keywords: Oceania, identity, indigenous, Indo-Fijian, postcolonialism, literature, history
    - Uy, Jamie. Star Wars and the Eco-Politics of Survival, 2021; 2021-0044 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2021-0044)
      From the scrappy Millennium Falcon to barren, backwater planets, the Star Wars universe revolves around junk, trash, and waste. Through the perspective of material ecocriticism, however, representations of so-called "dead" matter in Star Wars reveal how nonhuman elements of the environment are never truly inanimate. These representations prompt us to recognize the surprising "force of things," an experience which Jane Bennett summarizes as "thing-power," or "the curious ability of inanimate things to animate, to act, to produce effects dramatic and subtle" (Vibrant Matter 6). This capstone expands the boundaries of material ecocriticism, which has demonstrated relatively little interest in the thing-power of media, while bringing material ecocriticism to popular cinema. I analyze stereotypically inanimate matter or "lesser" life-forms (such as the Tusken Raiders, the Death Star, and carbonite) to argue that Star Wars casts the nonhuman as agentic across its sprawling storyworlds. Along the way, I track how eco-philosophy evolves throughout almost fifty years of Star Wars history. Analyzing Star Wars as a global transmedia phenomenon illuminates how our media environments and natural environments are enmeshed, embedded, and continuously interact. Ultimately, Star Wars advocates for an eco-politics of survival by expanding the definition of the "Anthropos" in the Anthropocene.
      Author provided keywords: Star Wars, material ecocriticism, science fiction, popular culture, Anthropocene
  - Music
    - Heo, Seonmin. Recreating Performance Styles of Fats Waller, Erroll Garner, and Art Tatum Through Computer Programming, 2014; 2014-0027; 77 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2014-0027)
      Major: Music, Economics
      Abstract: I created a computer program using Max, a visual programming language, to generate jazz piano solos that imitate the performance styles of Fats Waller, Erroll Garner, and Art Tatum. I explored the limitations of computer programming by first transcribing their performance recordings, analyzing patterns in their performance styles, and recreating jazz melodies according to these identified patterns that were encoded into the program.
      Transcription; Jazz; Music; Computer programming; Music
    - Nivia Obando, Manuel Jose. AUHDIO, 2014; 2014-0023; 76 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2014-0023)
      Major: Music. Online Project. Abstract: A monthly live music showcase and platform that features live music in unconventional and underutilized venues with the goal of vitalizing the music scene of Abu Dhabi.
      soundcloud.com/AUHDIO
      Community; Hip-hop; Songwriting; Music; United Arab Emirates; Abu Dhabi, United Arab Emirates; Music
    - Bello, Juliana. Ámame como Amas: A Music Capstone., 2016; 2016-0008; 7968; Ámame como Amas is a four-song EP that intersects with three different languages and several musical styles. It features covers of well known songs that rotate through the languages of English, Arabic, and Spanish, and the genres of electropop, Cuban and modern pop salsa, and traditional Arabic music. This EP brings together three groups of musicians thoroughly familiar with these styles of music so that their specialties might combine without facing the boundaries usually in place between their respective genres. The choice of English, Arabic, and Spanish reflects my personal experience in study of these languages and some of the musical and vocal traditions that have developed alongside them. (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2016-0008)
      Ámame como Amas is a four-song EP that intersects with three different languages and several musical styles. It features covers of well known songs that rotate through the languages of English, Arabic, and Spanish, and the genres of electropop, Cuban and modern pop salsa, and traditional Arabic music. This EP brings together three groups of musicians thoroughly familiar with these styles of music so that their specialties might combine without facing the boundaries usually in place between their respective genres. The choice of English, Arabic, and Spanish reflects my personal experience in study of these languages and some of the musical and vocal traditions that have developed alongside them.
    - de Keizer, Victoria. Music, Voice, and Agency: Response Mechanisms of Politically Marginalized Groups and the Case of the Rastafari Minority in Ethiopia., 2016; 2016-0017; 7967; This research project uses Minorities at Risk (MAR) data and an original ethnographic dataset to examine how politically marginalized groups respond to exclusion. Drawing on Albert Hirschman's theory of exit, voice, and loyalty, my analysis reveals global patterns in minority responses, while my case study of the Rastafari provides insight into the complex politics of inclusion and exclusion in Ethiopia from the 1950s to the present. Both these datasets demonstrate that groups who are excluded establish political agency through different modes of voice, which, in Rastafari communities, takes the form of Ethiopian reggae music. Although my research indicates that groups with political representation are more likely to express dissent through pressure group tactics, it suggests also that music can serve as an important platform for envisioning and negotiating political and cultural inclusion in the absence of formal representation. (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2016-0017)
      This research project uses Minorities at Risk (MAR) data and an original ethnographic dataset to examine how politically marginalized groups respond to exclusion. Drawing on Albert Hirschman's theory of exit, voice, and loyalty, my analysis reveals global patterns in minority responses, while my case study of the Rastafari provides insight into the complex politics of inclusion and exclusion in Ethiopia from the 1950s to the present. Both these datasets demonstrate that groups who are excluded establish political agency through different modes of voice, which, in Rastafari communities, takes the form of Ethiopian reggae music. Although my research indicates that groups with political representation are more likely to express dissent through pressure group tactics, it suggests also that music can serve as an important platform for envisioning and negotiating political and cultural inclusion in the absence of formal representation.
    - Chan, Garreth. Unheard Of: Creating Cinematic Soundscapes, 2017; 2017-0003; Unheard Of: Creating Cinematic Soundscapes comprised of developing all audio components for the following four film capstones: Alma (Jime Reyes), Acheevment (Gergő Varga), Mahaa (Yunbo Wu), and Thirty (Yi Yi Yeap). These audio components included my assumption of all the following roles: • Production Sound Mixer, Boom Operator, Sound Editor • Producer, Sound Designer, Music Supervisor • Composer, Performer, Recording Engineer • Foley Supervisor, Foley Artist, Foley Mixer • ADR Supervisor, ADR Mixer • Mixing Engineer The motivation of the capstone project came from my desire to explore further my previous experiences in designing music and sound for films and theater performances, specifically the notion and conscious use of silence (or lack thereof) in creating an effective sonic ambience. The question of using silence with emotional impact is in response to film director Henri Colpi's quote, "Above all, no gaps or holes, cry filmmakers with alarm. And if hole there be, plug it up with music," and offers a counterexample of using non-musical elements – in line with musical elements – to elicit similar emotional response. (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2017-0003)
      Unheard Of: Creating Cinematic Soundscapes comprised of developing all audio components for the following four film capstones: Alma (Jime Reyes), Acheevment (Gergő Varga), Mahaa (Yunbo Wu), and Thirty (Yi Yi Yeap). These audio components included my assumption of all the following roles: • Production Sound Mixer, Boom Operator, Sound Editor • Producer, Sound Designer, Music Supervisor • Composer, Performer, Recording Engineer • Foley Supervisor, Foley Artist, Foley Mixer • ADR Supervisor, ADR Mixer • Mixing Engineer The motivation of the capstone project came from my desire to explore further my previous experiences in designing music and sound for films and theater performances, specifically the notion and conscious use of silence (or lack thereof) in creating an effective sonic ambience. The question of using silence with emotional impact is in response to film director Henri Colpi's quote, "Above all, no gaps or holes, cry filmmakers with alarm. And if hole there be, plug it up with music," and offers a counterexample of using non-musical elements – in line with musical elements – to elicit similar emotional response.